Federico Massa

Ph.D. Student in Robotics, MSc in Physics

Via Francesco Pardi, 18
Pisa (PI) - Italy

\$\pi +39 347 7034248\$

\times fedemassa91@gmail.com

federicomassa.github.io



Professional Profile

My background is in Physics (BSc and MSc), which provided me with advanced physics, mathematics and statistics skills. In 2016, I started a collaboration with the Robotics Research Center "E.Piaggio" of the University of Pisa, where I started a Ph.D. in 2017 focusing on Autonomous Driving. I am currently part of *Roboteam-Italia*, one of the teams of Roborace, an autonomous full scale electric racing car competition. I have always had a strong inclination toward software development (especially for robotics applications), which led me to delve into the development of the team perception system (based on lidar sensors) and on a driving simulator that the team uses to test the whole perception-control pipeline.

Education

2017–present Ph.D. Student in Robotics, Research Center E. Piaggio.

2016–2017 Research contract, Research Center E. Piaggio.

2013–2016 MSc in Physics, University of Pisa, 110/110 cum laude.

2010–2013 BSc in Physics, University of Cagliari, 110/110 cum laude.

2005–2010 Scienfitic High School Diploma, Lic. Sc. Pitagora (Selargius), 100/100 cum laude.

Experience

2019 Roborace event, Zala Zone (Hungary), Perception module developer for Roboteam-Italia team.

2019–present **Teaching assistant**, *University of Pisa (Italy)*, "Introduction to ROS" for the Distributed Robotic Systems course, MSc in Robotics and Automation.

2018—present **Perception module team leader**, Research Center E. Piaggio (Italy), Roboteam-Italia team, Developing a lidar-based mapping and localisation system for autonomous racing cars.

2018–present **Simulation module team leader**, Research Center E. Piaggio (Italy), Roboteam-Italia team, Developing a simulator based on Unreal Engine 4 to simulate the whole Roborace autonomous racing competition.

2018 Roborace event, Berlin (Germany), Perception module developer for Roboteam-Italia team.

2018 Introduction to Mobile Robotics, ITIS Livorno, held a workshop on Robotics for High School students.

2016 Master thesis, Geneva (Switzerland), Brief stay at CERN under the ITk group (ATLAS experiment).

2016 Workshop, Alghero (Italy), Participation to the "XIII Seminar on Software for Nuclear, Subnuclear and Applied Physics": Geant4 framework and GPU programming.

Core Skills

- Lidar-based mapping and localization
- Driving simulators development
- o Classical/Relativistic/Quantum Physics
- Statistical data analysis

- $\ \, \circ \ \, {\rm Particle/Kalman \ filters \ implementation} \\$
- Advanced calculus and differential calculus
- Monte Carlo simulations
- Reinforcement Learning

Programming Skills

- \circ C++ (strong)
- Matlab/Simulink
- Multithreaded applications programming
- Qt/Qt Quick framework
- Python

- ROS
- Unreal Engine 4
- PhysX basics
- Bash scripting

Languages

- Italian (mother tongue)
- English (fluent)
- Spanish (intermediate)

Publications

[1] D. Caporale, A. Settimi, F. Massa, F. Amerotti, A. Corti, A. Fagiolini, M. Guiggiani, A. Bicchi, L. Pallottino: "Towards the Design of Robotic Drivers for Full-Scale Self-Driving Racing Cars", IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA), 2019

[2] D. Caporale, A. Fagiolini, L. Pallottino, A. Settimi, A. Biondo, F. Amerotti, F. Massa, S. De Caro, A. Corti, L. Venturini: "A Planning and Control System for Self-Driving Racing Vehicles", IEEE Research and Technologies for Society and Industry (RTSI), Sept. 2018